Guide to the Holocaust Photograph Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Holocaust photograph collection
1943-1951
MS 1854
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
The collection consists of photographs of Holocaust atrocities, concentration camps liberated by the armies of the United States and Great Britain in 1945, and subsequent war crimes trials.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Judaica Collection Curator, 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Photographs are arranged in three series: I. Concentration camps and other sites of atrocities. II. Individuals. III. Trials.
Scope and Contents
The collection is comprised of 152 photographs of concentration camps liberated by the armies of the United States and Great Britain in 1945 and the war crimes trials that followed. The bulk of the photographs date from April - May 1945, though many were released at a later date. Most of the photographs have caption labels. Only a few photographers are mentioned by name. The collection is organized in alphabetical order under three headings: Concentration camps and other sites of atrocities, Individuals, and Trials. The location of the image(s) is given, followed in brackets by the country, liberating army if known, number of photographs, and relevant information.
The majority of the photographs are included under the first heading and focus primarily on the liberation of concentration camps in Germany, although there are photographs taken in Austria, Belgium, Czechoslovakia, France, the Netherlands, Poland, and the Soviet Union. These photographs portray the atrocities of the camps including images of the dead, the workings of the camps, and the reactions of liberated prisoners and liberating soldiers. Many of these photographs depict German civilians compelled to witness the atrocities of the camps and to act as gravediggers and pallbearers for the victims. There are five photographs of General Eisenhower reviewing the camps at Ohrdruf (related to Buchenwald) and Gotha and several which include a delegation from the U.S. Congress to Buchenwald.
Under the second heading, Individuals, there are four photographs depicting two American P.O.W.s rescued from German camps. The Trials contain images of the war crimes trials in Germany and Italy after the war. These are photographs of the judicial process. Although focused on the Nazi defendants, they include images of judges, lawyers, witnesses, and the evidence introduced. There are fifteen photographs from the Nuremberg trials, April - May 1947, and one photograph from the trial of Adolf Hitler in Munich, October 1948, in which the verdict is read to an empty chair.
Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945) -- Photographs; World War, 1939-1945 -- Concentration camps -- Liberation; Photographs
- Inventory
  - Concentration camps and other sites of atrocities
    - Altendorn [Germany, 2 photographs, commandant of liberated camp led away], 1945 April (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bergen Belsen [Germany, British Army, 21 photographs], 1945 April-May (Box 1, Folder 2 - 3)
    - Berlin [Germany, 1 photograph], 1945 October (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Buchenwald [Germany, U.S. Army, 16 photographs, including several with U.S. Congressional delegation], 1945 April-May (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Ohrdruf [Germany, 8 photographs, 2 of General Eisenhower reviewing the camp], 1945 April (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Weimar [Germany, 3 photographs], 1945 April (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Dachau [Germany, U.S. Army, 2 photographs], 1945 May (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Kaufbeuren [Germany, 1 photograph], 1945 July (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Dortmund [Germany, 3 photographs], 1945 April (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Dossel [Germany, 1 photograph], 1945 April (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Essen [Germany, 1 photograph], 1945 April (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Falkenau [Czechoslavakia, 1 photograph], 1945 May (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Gardelegen [Germany, 4 photographs], 1945 April (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Gotha [Germany, U.S. Army, 5 photographs, including 3 of General Eisenhower reviewing the camp], 1945 April (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Gusen-Mühlhausen [Austria, 3 photographs], 1945 May (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Hadamar [Germany, 1 photograph, insane asylum], 1945 May (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Hemer [Germany, 3 photographs], 1945 April-May (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Immergrath [Germany, 1 photograph], 1945 April (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Katyn Forest [Russia, 2 photographs], 1943 May (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Lambach [Austria, U.S. Army, 2 photographs], 1945 May (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Landesberg [Germany, 1 photograph], 1945 May (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Leipzig [Germany, 1 photograph], 1945 April (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Limburg [Germany, 3 photographs], 1945 April (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Lodz [Poland, 1 photograph, execution of a Jew], [1945 Dec] (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Ludwigslust [Germany, 1 photograph], 1945 May (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Malmedy [Belgium, 3 photographs], 1945 Jan, 1946 April (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Natzweiler-Struthof [France, 5 photographs], 1944 December 2 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Heppenheim [Germany, 1 photograph], 1945 April 7 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Nordhausen [Germany, 12 photographs, slave labor camp liberated by U.S. 3rd Armored Division], 1945 April (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Nuenberg [Germany, 4 photographs], 1945 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Oswiecim [Germany, 1 photograph, remains from a mass grave buried in Buffalo, NY], 1948 February (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Schwerin [Germany, 1 photograph], 1945 May (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Stavelot [Belgium, 2 photographs], 1945 January (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Suttrop [Germany, 1 photograph], 1945 May (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Vught [the Netherlands, 1 photograph], 1944 December (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Wobbelin [Germany, 1 photograph], 1945 May (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Zeitheim [Germany, Soviet zone, 1 photograph], 1946 September (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Individuals
    - Abrams, Pvt. Alvin L. [1 photograph, P.O.W.], 1945 April (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Demler, Pvt. Joseph [3 photographs, P.O.W.], 1945 May-July (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Trials
    - Ahrweiler [Germany, 2 photographs], 1945 June (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Dachau [Germany, 1 photograph], 1945 November (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Italy [3 photographs], 1946 Jan, 1948 May (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Landsberg [Germany, 1 photograph, military court], 1951 September (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Munich [Germany, 1 photograph, Adolf Hitler tried in absentia], 1948 October (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Nuremberg [Germany, 15 photographs], 1947 May (Box 1, Folder 46 - 47)
    - Ruhr-area [Germany, 1 photograph, 13 Ruhr magnates arrested by British Army], 1945 December (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Wiesbaden [Germany, 2 photographs, military trial], 1945 October (Box 1, Folder 49)